Finding Aid for Theodore Wesley Koch Papers, 1894-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Theodore Wesley Koch Papers 1894-1941
Koch, Theodore Wesley, 1871-1941.
851701 Aa 2; UAm
Librarian at the Library of Congress, University of Michigan and Northwestern University, and bibliophile. Correspondence, articles and pamphlets, papers relating to his books and articles, and topical files relating to his interest in Carnegie Libraries, literary forgeries, the work of the American Library Association's Library War Service during World War I, library Americanization programs, 1919-1921, and the library building of University of Michigan; also photographs.
12 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Dorothy Koch Bestor (donor no. 4120 ) and came to the library in 1964 and 1973. Other files were transferred from the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1278 ).
The collection is open to research.
Theodore W. Koch (1871-1941) was for many years a prominent figure in American librarianship. After completing his M.A. degree at Harvard University in 1894, he was employed by the library at Cornell University to catalogue the Fiske Collection of Dante material. He worked at the Library of Congress from 1902 to1904 and then moved on to the library of the University of Michigan, where he served as assistant librarian,1904-1905, and librarian,1905-1916.
A dispute with the Board of Regents led to his dismissal from his post at the University of Michigan so he returned to the Library of Congress, where he served as chief of the order division. During World War I he was involved in the American Library Association's Library War Service program to provide books for soldiers. In 1919 he was appointed librarian of Northwestern University where he served until his death in 1941.
The Koch papers are very incomplete for the part of his career before he went to Northwestern. Much of the earliest correspondence deals with the gathering of material for his "A Portfolio of Carnegie Libraries," Very little material on his work at the University of Michigan has survived, although a few reports from Byron A. Finney on the operation of the library and copies of Koch's proposal for a new library in 1915 are included in the collection.
Although the collection is much larger for the years after 1919, it is apparent that even for these years many of his professional files were either retained by the Northwestern University Library or destroyed. There is surprisingly little information on the activities of the A.L.A. or other professional organizations. Much of the correspondence consists of family and personal mail rather than the activities of the Northwestern library.
A high proportion of the material from this period relates to the writing and publication of his many books and pamphlets. Although Koch's files on Carnegie libraries, literary forgeries, the A.L.A. Library War Service, and Americanization programs may be of interest to scholars, many of his publications involved the translation and publication of works aimed merely at bibliophiles. These works were often published by such groups as the Caxton Club of Chicago or the Roxburgh Club of San Francisco which are interested in printing as an art form.
Subjects:
American Library Association.; Americanization.; Koch, Theodore Wesley, 1871-1941.; Libraries--United States.; Northwestern University (Evanston, Ill.); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Library.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Apostles Club (University of Michigan); Detroit Public Library.; Ellis Island Immigration Station (N.Y. and N.J.); Emigration and immigration.; Koch, Theodore Wesley, 1871-1941.; Libraries--United States.; University of Michigan. Law Library.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. Medical Library.; World War, 1914-1918.
Contributors:
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Barrett, Albert M. (Albert Moore), 1871-1936.; Belden, Charles Francis Dorr, 1870-1931.; Boucke, Ewald A. (Ewald Augustus), 1871-; Bowker, R. R. (Richard Rogers), 1848-1933.; Champion, Edouard, 1882-1938.; Cross, Arthur Lyon, 1873-1940.; Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; Douglas, Lloyd C. (Lloyd Cassel), 1877-1951.; Evans, Charles, 1850-1935.; Fife, Robert Herndon, 1871-1958.; Finney, Byron Alfred, 1849-1938.; Foote, Henry Wilder, 1875-1964.; Garland, Hamlin, 1860-1940.; Gillette, Fredericka Botsford, 1875-; Goodrich, Francis Lee Dewey, 1877-1962.; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.; Huebsch, B. W. (Benjamin W.), 1876-1964.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Jordan, Myra Beach, 1863-1946.; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984.; Lorch, Emil, 1870-1963.; MacChesney, Nathan William, 1878-1954.; McMurtrie, Douglas C. (Douglas Crawford), 1888-1944.; Mason, William Smith, b. 1866.; Milan, Carl Hastings, 1884-1963.; National Committee of the United States for the Restoration of the University of Louvain.; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908.; Otis, William Augustus, 1855-1929.; Putnam, Herbert, 1861-1955.; Richardson, Ernest Cushing, 1860-1939.; Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.; Scott, Walter Dill, 1869-1955.; Snyder, Franklin Bliss, 1884-1958.; Stevenson, Burton Egbert, 1872-1962.; Todd, Albert May, 1850-1931.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Wilson, Halsey William, 1868-1954.; Zweig, Stefan, 1881-1942.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1894-June 1921, 36 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1921-October 1926, 36 folders (Box 2)
  - November 1926-October 1930, 34 folders (Box 3)
  - November 1930-April 1937, 33 folders (Box 4)
  - May 1937-1950, 18 folders (Box 5)
- Biographical information
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Articles, Pamphlets, and other writings
  - Undated 1900-1928, 10 folders (Box 5)
  - 1929-1931 (Box 6)
  - 1933-1934 (Box 6)
  - 1935-1940 (Box 6)
  - 1941-1950 (Box 6)
  - Book: Les Livres a la Guerre 1920 (Box 6)
- Topical Files
  (about libraries and other interests)
  - Newspaper clippings,1901-1950, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Carnegie Libraries
    - Papers undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings 1902-1911, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Printed material undated, 1900-1906, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Dante and Dante Society, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Literary forgeries, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Library War Service during World War I, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Library War Service (Box 7)
    (newspaper clippings about)
  - University of Michigan Library building 1915, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Americanization materials, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Americanization (newspaper clippings about), 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Americanization (printed material concerning), 5 folders (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Chronological Papers
  - Undated 1893-1950, 16 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings 1922-1928 (Box 8)
- Papers concerning books and articles
  - Reading in and out of College (Box 8)
  - University Libraries, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - The British Museum (Box 8)
  - General Libraries, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - General Libraries, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Reading--a vice or a virtue, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - The Mirror of the Parisian Bibliophile, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - NY Republic--Lacroix (Box 9)
  - Orlando Furioso-Aristo (Box 9)
  - Eden Anto-Fogazzaro (Box 9)
  - Milkau's Handbook (Box 9)
  - Geschicte der Bibliot ken--Hessel, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - The Sigismond Inheritance-Uzanne (Box 9)
  - Francesco Colonoa--Nodier (Box 9)
  - The Bibliomaniac--Nodier (Box 9)
  - The Assembly of Books, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - The Essence of Poetry, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - A Bibliophile's hell-Asselineau (Box 10)
  - Bibliomania--Flaubert (Box 10)
  - The French Pastry Cook--Dumas (Box 10)
  - A Letter on Bibliophiles--Duhamel (Box 10)
  - Books in the War (Box 10)
  - The German Book Exhibit, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - The Florentine Book Fair, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Tales for Bibliophile, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - The German Book Crisis (Box 10)
  - College and University Library Statistics, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Books are the Gateway to the World--Stefan Zweig (Box 10)
  - The Old Book Peddler--Stefan Zweig, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - The Invisible Collection, Thanks to Books & Notes--Stefan Zweig (Box 10)
  - Bibliofons-Babler (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Books, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Miscellanea, 10 folders (Box 11)
  - Student notes, 10 folders (Box 11)
    (include notes and essays from classes at the University of Pennsylvania and Harvard)
- Photographs
  - TWK portrait and group photos (Apostles Club) (Box 12)
  - Americanization and Immigration
    - Americanization and citizenship classes circa 1920 (Box 12)
    - Immigration circa 1918-1920, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Deportation scene 1919 (Box 12)
    - Japanese immigrants in California (Box 12)
  - Libraries
    - Public
      - Detroit Public Library (children's roam, auto deliveries, branches) (Box 12)
      - Galesburg, Illinois (Box 12)
      - New York City (Box 12)
      - Michigan (Box 12)
      - Various (non-Michigan), 2 folders (Box 12)
    - College and University
      - University of Michigan
        - Law Library (Box 12)
        - Medical Library (Box 12)
        - Various (Box 12)
      - Michigan (various) (Box 12)
      - Various (non-Michigan), 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Other
      - John Rylands Library (Box 12)
      - State Law Library, Hartford, Connecticut (Box 12)
  - World War 1 1914-1918
    - American Library Association, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - American Red Cross (Box 12)
    - YMCA (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook containing postcards of library buildings (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook of library plans (Box 12)
Selective Index of Correspondents
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.
1935, 1936
Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840 -1925.
Nov. 21, 1904
Barrett, Albert Moore, 1871-1936.
Undated, Aug. 24, Nov. 10, 1919, Aug. 11, 1923, Jan. 1, 1924, Sept. 12, 1925, July 11, 1926, Jan. 2, 1927, Oct. 21, 1928, Apr. 5, 1930, July 12, 1932, June 11, July 13, 1933, 1934, Mar. 1, Nov. 12, 1936.
Belden, Charles Francis Dorr, 1870-1931.
1925, 1926, 1929
Boucke, Ewald A. (Ewald Augustus), 1871-1943.
May 17, June 12, 1920, Feb. 7, Mar. 27, 1926, July 12, 1928, Dec. 6, 1929
Bowker, R. R. (Richard Rogers), 1848-1933.
Aug. 19, Oct 19, 1915, Mar. 24, 1916, Sept. 19, 1916, May 16, 1927, Dec. 19, 1928
Champion, Edouard, 1882-1938.
1922, 1923, 1924, 1925, 1926, 1927, 1928, 1929, 1930, 1931, 1932, 1933, 1934, 1935, 1936
Cross, Arthur Lyon, 1873-1940.
Aug. 16, 1915
Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.
Mar. 22, 1904
Douglas, Lloyd C. (Lloyd Cassel), 1877-1951.
Feb. 21, 1918
Evans, Charles, 1850-1935.
Apr. 1, 1925, Aug. 9, 1925
Fife, Robert Herndon, 1871-1958.
1925, 1926
Finney, Byron Alfred, 1849-1938.
Aug. 31, 1903, 1906, 1907, 1908, 1909, 1910, May 26, 1914, Aug. 4, 1916, Oct. 10, 1916, June 6, 1919, Feb. 23, 1920, Mar. 2, 1920, Feb. 1, 1923, May 13, 1925, June 5, 1926, Mar. 29, 1932, Feb. 13, 1938, Apr. 29, 1938.
Foote, Henry Wilder, 1875-1964.
Jan. 7, 1925, June 17, 1926, July 16, 1926.
Garland, Hamlin, 1860-1940.
Dec. 12, 1936, Dec. 22, 1938, Jan. 20, 1940
Gillette, Fredericka Botsford, 1875-
July 26, 1915, June 16, 1926, Dec. 9, 1926, Jan. 20, 1930, Aug. 6, 1930, Nov. 7, 1930, Mar. 31, Apr. 16, 1931, Sept. 15, 1932, Sept. 25, 1933, Apr. 24, 1934, 1936, 1937, 1938, 1939, 1940
Goodrich, Francis Lee Dewey, 1877-1962.
1914, 1915, Jan. 28, 1918, Dec. 4, 1919, Nov. 17, 1920, Aug. 26, 1921, June 12, Dec. 3, 1926, 1929, Jan. 10, 1930, June 10, 1930, Feb. 16, 1932, July 28, 1935, Nov. 18, Dec. 3, 1937, Feb. 6, 1941.
Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.
Aug. 9, 1895.
Huebsch, B.W., (Benjamin W.), 1876-1964.
June 16, 1925, Dec. 19, 26, 1933
Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.
Apr. 6, 1915
Jordan, Myra Beach, 1863-1946.
Dec. 27, 1937, Sept. 12, 1939, July 3, 1940
Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984.
Nov. 20, Nov. 28, 1923.
Lorch, Emil, 1870-1963.
July 6, 1923, July 2, 1925, Nov. 13, 1926, June 6, 27, 1928
MacChesney, Nathan William 1878-1954.
1923, 1924, 1926, June 19, 1940
McMurtrie, Douglas C., (Douglas Crawford), 1888-1944.
1927, 1928, Aug. 29, 1929
Mason, William Smith, 1866.
1922, 1925, 1926, Apr. 16, 1931, Dec. 28, 1934, July 17, 1935, 1937, 1938, Oct. 5, 1939
Milan, Carl Hastings, 1884-1963.
1919-1925
Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908.
Mar. 1, 1897, May 13, 1897, 1900
Otis, William Augustus, 1855-1929.
1904, 1905, 1906
Putnam, Herbert, 1861-1955.
May 2, 1904, Sept. 12, 1913, July 31, 1915, Dec. 13, 1915, Jan. 15, Aug. 19, 1916, Sept. 5, Sept. 25, 1916, July 25, 1918, 1919, Mar. 12, 1920, Jan. 17, 1923, Apr. 27, 1939
Richardson, Ernest Cushing, 1860-1939.
1915, 1916, 1919
Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.
Mar. 1, 1915, July 20, 1915
Scott, Walter Dill, 1869-1955.
Nov. 4, 1923, Mar. 12, 1924, Feb. 16, 1925, May 27, 1925, Jan. 30, 1926, July 26, 1927, May 2, 1929, Aug. 30, 1929, Apr. 21, 1931, Jan. 9, 1933, May 8, 1934, Nov. 1, 1935, June 17, 1936, June 26, 1936, June 13, 1938, May 5, 1939
Snyder, Franklin Bliss, 1884-1958.
Undated, Apr. 13, 1939, Nov. 28, 1939
Stevenson, Burton Egbert, 1872-1962.
1920, June 2, 1921
Todd, Albert May, 1850-1931.
June 26, 1926, Nov. 21, 1926, Jan. 22, 1927
White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.
Aug. 29, 1904
Wilson, Halsey William, 1868-1954.
1917, May 25, 1921, Nov. 4, Nov. 17, Dec. 16, 1926, Jan. 15, 1927, Aug. 29, Dec. 2, 1929, June 17,1931, May 7, Aug. 6, 1936
Zweig, Stefan, 1881-1942.
1931, 1932, 1937, 1938, 1939